<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the spirits working upon the minds of men in the several ages of the Christian church in a visitation sermon before the Right Reverend Father in God, Henry Lord Bishop of London, at Burntwood in Essex, Septemb. 14, 1680 / by Richard Hollingworth.</title>
            <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26432</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09463847</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09463847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1310:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the spirits working upon the minds of men in the several ages of the Christian church in a visitation sermon before the Right Reverend Father in God, Henry Lord Bishop of London, at Burntwood in Essex, Septemb. 14, 1680 / by Richard Hollingworth.</title>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Hen. Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts II, 17-18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43183:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE SPIRITS Working upon the minds of Men, in the ſeveral Ages of the <hi>CHRISTIAN CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN A <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation Sermon,</hi> BEFORE The Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>HENRY</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London;</hi> at <hi>Burntwood</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Septemb. 14. 1680.</p>
            <p>BY RICHARD HOLLINGWORTH, M. A. Vicar of <hi>Weſt-Ham,</hi> near <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Hen. Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun,</hi> at the Weſt-end of S. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:43183:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43183:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Viſitation Sermon</hi> UPON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 2.17, 18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days (ſaith God) I will pour out of my Spirit upon all fleſh, and your Sons and your Daughters ſhall Propheſie, and your young men ſhall ſee Viſions, and your old men ſhall dream dreams.</p>
                  <p>And on my Servants, and on my Hand maidens I will pour out in thoſe days of my Spirit, and they ſhall Propheſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a very great kindneſs as well as juſtice that we owe to our judgments and underſtandings, to lodge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them but what is agreeable to Truth and Reaſon; but what can be accounted for when we are called before others to vindicate our ſelves; but what is in its conſequences and effects really ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the needs and neceſſities, as well as to the pleaſures and delights of the Soul. And thoſe men that are eaſily impoſed upon, and ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be diſpoſed of, either by the Rhetorick or Flattery of others, they are very falſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to that excellent Being which God hath given them.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43183:3"/>
            <p>And amongſt many other truths, in which the ſoul of man ought carefully to concern it ſelf, I think, and that I am ſure, not without proper grounds, the Notion of the Spirit of God is one, the not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whereof aright, hath had as pernicious an influence upon the Church of God as any thing Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry informs us of, and to reckon up the ſeveral evils that have ſprung from hence, would be an endleſs piece of work. From hence have ariſen debates and ſtrifes, which have not had their period without loſs of life, as well as reputation: from hence have men grown proud and ſawcy, and adopted all the ſilly and groundleſs conceits of their own brains into the fundamental and abſolute neceſſaries of Religion, and have been hugely troubleſome to all the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, if with an equal zeal they would not as well propagate and ſpread abroad, as ſuck in their fancies and ſickly imaginations. From hence have ariſen thoſe ſeparations of men from one another, and that with the vileſt reflections upon each other that could be; calling, nay dooming each other as limbs of Antichriſt, and ſpawn of Hell, as perſons that ſtand in a direct oppoſition to the Kingdom of the Lord Jeſus, and with all might endeavouring the utter ruin and extirpation of one another: Yea, in a word, the quarrels about the Spirit have run ſo high, and men have conceited themſelves ſo acted by it, that they have altered, as far as they could, the very nature of things, and have made thoſe things lawful by neceſſity and providence,<note place="margin">Witneſs the Murther of the late King.</note> which Scripture and right Reaſon have determined before hand as utterly unlawful.</p>
            <p>And therefore certainly it ſtands us all in ſtead to ſet this Notion right in our heads, that ſo we may not fall into thoſe inconveniencies, which a wrong ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43183:3"/>of it is naturally attended with. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which piece of ſervice, I have made choice of theſe words, and my buſineſs from them is to ſhew what Spirit it is that hath been enjoyed in the Goſpel, and by vertue of its appearance in the world; where we will conſider the neceſſity of different adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſame Spirit, and the great miſtakes thoſe men labour under, who expect or vapour of the ſame powerful and immediate helps and aſſiſtances now, that the Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Lord were ſo plentifully furniſhed withal at their firſt ſetting out, in order to the ſettlement of Chriſtianity in the world; and for the better carrying on this great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, we will conſider theſe ſeveral things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What Spirit it was that the Apoſtles had after the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt. Now it is plain that the Spirit of the Apoſtles was ſuitable to the great Errand they were ſent about, to the great work they were to finiſh; for as the caſe was extraordinary, ſo was the Spirit that aſſiſted them: and therefore we find they were able to work Miracles, the great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation to any truth whatſoever, and which God hath all along uſed upon great occaſions; they were able to ſpeak with tongues, ſuch as they were as much unacquainted withal before, as a new-born Babe is with the language of his Countrey. They had the giſt of diſcerning Spirits, with many other things which were mighty neceſſary, conſidering what they went about; for their Errand was to pull down the Model of the Jewiſh worſhip, a great part whereof had been ſet up by God himſelf; to take down the pale, whereby the Jews had for many hundred years been peculiarly ſeparated from the reſt of the world, and upon which account they valued themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reſt of the world: They were to convince
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43183:4"/>them that their Sacrifices did ceaſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> muſt be frequented under other Notions, and upon other accounts than it was when their ceremonial ſervice was in being; and you that know the force of education, muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this was hard work, and needed great courage, and as great an evidence of the truth of their Commiſſion. For when new things are to be ſetled in the room of ſomething that was fixed before by a Divine Warrant, it had need of ſome peculiar excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in its nature, or ſome more than ordinary evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, before it ought to have any admittance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sons of men; for things well founded, ought not upon eaſie terms to be overturned: And therefore upon this account, the Goſpel being ſent on purpoſe to make void the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo far as it was Judicial or Ceremonial; and the Law having been ſetled by God himſelf, there was great reaſon that ſuch as were the immediate inſtruments of ſo great an undertaking, ſhould have a proportionable commiſſion and ſtrength to do it with.</p>
            <p>And as the Apoſtles ſtood in need of this extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Spirit upon the <hi>Jews</hi> account, ſo alſo upon the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> who, though they were Servants to a falſe Religion, yet they believed not ſo, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it muſt needs be a very hard task to unfix them, and bring them to an impartial conſideration of thoſe convincing proofs the Apoſtles gave of their being ſent by God. They were trained up in the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch Gods as did no ways oblige them to any engagement againſt their Luſts; nay, the worſhipping of whom was in part a fulfilling of their luſts; and as we find over all thoſe parts of the preſent world, that are miſtaken in the objects of their worſhip; ſo no doubt it was then, they had a mighty fond eſteem for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43183:4"/>their Idols, and were ready to judge, and that with the greateſt ſeverity, every perſon that did not bow down to them. And Oh, how hard a thing it was then for the Apoſtles to conteſt with prejudices foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in education, in principles ſucked from thoſe they loved moſt, to wit, their Parents: and therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account there was great need of an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Spirit, whereby men might be convinced of the truth of their perſons as well as their doctrins: Alas, had it not been for this, the Goſpel would have been nipped in its firſt budding forth, and it would have been a downright impoſſibility for ſo great a part of the world to have been impoſed upon by ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of illiterate perſons as the Apoſtles, before the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt were.</p>
            <p>Can you imagine that ſuch Learned men as <hi>Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> and other perſons brought up in the Schools at <hi>Athens,</hi> who well underſtood the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and connexion of things, would have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the pretences of ſuch bold and rude perſons, who could ſhew no reaſon at all beyond their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident aſſertions for what they ſaid? No, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. And by the way, this one thing ſhews the great neceſſity of human Learning, and is a ſufficient confutation of all thoſe <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> who do revile it; to wit, that what the Apoſtles wanted of it, upon the ſcore of education, God ſupplied by Miracle. Well but</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider how long this extraordinary Spirit continued in the Church; for that it is ceaſed, and that no man can now pretend to it, is a plain caſe, becauſe we daily experience it: for he that pretends to the ſame ſpirit the Apoſtles had, muſt do the ſame things, or elſe he is mighty vain, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues his underſtanding to be much impaired.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43183:5"/>
            <p>Now in anſwer to this, it is certain that God, who is never wanting to what he promiſes, nor to thoſe needs and neceſſities which his wiſdom and goodneſs conſpire to anſwer, was not wanting to his Church in the firſt Ages thereof, ſo long as they had any work to do, like to what firſt they ſet upon; that is, ſo long as they had new Countreys or People to ſpread this Goſpel abroad amongſt: And therefore we find in Hiſtory that this extraordinary Spirit continued more or lefs for about 400 years in the Church of God, and men wrought Miracles, and thereby convinced Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers; though about that time, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> tells us, they were not ſo numerous and plentiful as they were before; and the reaſon was, becauſe there was no ſuch need of them, and a little after they ceaſed. And this we may aſſert, notwithſtanding the boaſts of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who indeed, inſtead of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming men in the Chriſtian Religion, by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended miracles, do, if men be conſiderate, rather expoſe it to their ſcorn and cenſure; ſo ridiculous are the ſtories they tell, and upon ſuch ſlight and pitiful grounds do they pretend their Miracles are wrought. And therefore, I ſay, when the occaſion and reaſon of working Miracles ceaſed, then God in Wiſdom ſuſpended that great and mighty power wherewith he had accompanied good men before; and Kings proving Nurſing-fathers, and Queens Nurſing-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Church, the Goſpel being a National Religion in moſt Countreys, and that which youth was brought up in at firſt; and there being ſo full an evidence on its ſide, taken from the purity of its doctrine, the innocence of its deſign, the multitude of Miracles that awaited its firſt appearance, and other concurring teſtimonies of equal force; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men are now to look for no other Spirit but what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43183:5"/>is neceſſary for their needs and neceſſities as they are Chriſtians, which brings me to the third thing to be conſidered of, and that is</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. Notwithſtanding the ceaſing of this extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Spirit, yet there is a ſpirit continued to the Church of God ſufficiently helpful to men, ſuitable to their neceſſities, and to what God requires of them, in order to be partakers of his bleſſings. God is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver behind-hand with his Creatures, but his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſtands ready to aſſiſt them with ſuch Auxiliary forces as they really ſtand in need of, and no man ſhall ever complain that he periſhes for lack of any thing that God hath promiſed; the death of men muſt be laid at their own doors, and had they not been wanting to themſelves, Heaven had been their portion, and the lot of their Inheritance; and as God ſaid to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo he may ſay to all Chriſtians whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>O you Sons of men, you have deſtroyed your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we enter into a large field of diſcourſe, and I wiſh my thoughts and meditations may do juſtice and right to the matter under hand, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al anſwer your expectation in a thing ſo really mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentous and concerning. I ſay then, that though God hath thought good to withdraw the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Spirit, yet he is with his Church and People to the end of the World, by affording them ſuch aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are requiſite for their ſerving of him.</p>
            <p>And this is a Doctrine that hath ſo univerſally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Church of God, that the <hi>Pelagian</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie that aſſerts Man by the ſtrength of his faculties, improved by Scripture and Reaſon, by the objective evidence that is in things, might attain to ſuch a ſtate of mind, as to render him fit for Gods favour while here, and his eternal glory hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43183:6"/>
            <p>But though this was a Doctrin generally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, yet for all that, the miſtakes about the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, the confounding the extraordinary and ordinary ſpirit, the miſinterpreting ſeveral places of Scripture, which ſpeak of the effuſion of the Spirit in the laſt days, particularly that of my Text, the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of the Spirit in oppoſition to human Learning, and the exerciſe of our Reaſon; the patronizing of our own folly and wickedneſs, by pretences to a more immediate guidance and direction of the Spirit of God: I ſay theſe things have done a world of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to Religion and civil Society together; they have forced men out of their proper places, and been the original of ſo much pride and vanity of ſpirit, that Children as it were have riſen up againſt the Ancients, and every Novice hath taken upon him to pitty his betters, and to be a director of the People; and therefore certainly it is a thing of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to every man, to ſet this Notion right in his mind, that ſo he may not, like every little Child, be toſſed too and fro with every wind of doctrin, and that his judgment may not be enſlaved to every bold pretender that covers a Woolfiſh nature with Sheeps cloathing.</p>
            <p>Now that Spirit which awaits good men in this world, give me leave to give you this account of, which if but well conſidered, will (I am certain) ſtrengthen you againſt all thoſe addreſſes that ſin or errour at any time make to you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Spirit which now affiſts good men in this life, works upon them according to what they know; it brings no new Notices of things to them, but ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates upon thoſe they by their own labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry have collected and got together. For did it affiſt us not only with ſtrength and reſolution of mind
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43183:6"/>to adhere to what we know, but with the knowledge of things themſelves, without any inquiries of our own, all labour and diligence would be diſcouraged, and he that lived the moſt idle life, might be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to as due apprehenſions of things, as the moſt ſtudious and ſolitary perſon whatſoever; which if any man can give me an evidence of, I will let go this firſt aſſertion: but if I hold it till I meet with ſuch an inſtance, I believe I ſhall die of the ſame opinion I am now of. And therefore thoſe men that pretend to new lights, to more glorious diſcoveries, to more large manifeſtations of the mind and will of God than former Ages have been acquainted with, why theſe men run up and down the World with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, whereby they may indeed make the ſilly world mad, but I am ſure they will never make if wiſer or better, for there is no ſuch thing as new Lights; and when the New Teſtament was ſealed up, God curſed any man that added to the words of that Book, and he had certainly been wanting to his Church, if they had wanted any neceſſary to ſalvation, which he hath ſince revealed.</p>
            <p>No, no, I ſay again, the Spirit of God now brings no new things, but its buſineſs is to ſet the old ones upon our hearts and ſouls, to ſtrengthen our good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes for an holy life, to enlighten our dark faculties, whereby we may ſee the beauty and excellency of thoſe Divine objects that are propoſed to our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and to excite our affections to a love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the worth and value of thoſe things, in which our ſouls are more immediately concerned; and if any man appear, let him by looks and winks pretend to never ſo much Heavenly-mindedneſs, yet I ſay, if the man appear amongſt you with promiſes of further diſcoveries of the way and Kingdom of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43183:7"/>the Lord Jeſus, than the Chriſtian world hath yet been acquainted with, look upon him as an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor, as the Devils Agent, who comes on purpoſe to diſturb men in the good old way, through which the bleſſed Apoſtles, the noble Army of Martyrs, the excellent Saints in Primitive times, travelled to the New <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and this head I cannot leave, till I have given you an account what one of the greateſt Scholars this latter Age hath produced, ſays con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hales</hi>'s Golden Remains.</note> The effects of the Spirit (ſays he) as far as they concern inſtruction and knowledge, are not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar informations for reſolution in any doubtful caſes, for this were plainly Revelation; but as the Angel, who was ſent to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> informs him not, but ſends him to <hi>Peter</hi> to School; ſo the Spirit teaches not, but ſtirs up in us a deſire to learn; deſire to learn makes us thirſty after the means, and pious ſedulity and carefulneſs makes us watchful in the choice and diligent uſe of our means. The promiſe to the Apoſtles of the Spirit of God, which ſhould lead them into all truth, was made good unto them by private and ſecret informing their underſtandings, with the knowledge of high and heavenly myſteries, which as yet had never entered into the conceit of any man; the ſame promiſe is made good to us, but fulfilled after another manner; for what was written in their hearts by revelation for our inſtruction, have they writ in Books to us, for information otherwiſe than out of theſe Books, the Spirit ſpeaks not: When the Spirit regenerates a man, it infuſes no knowledge of any point of faith, but ſends him to the Church and to the Scriptures; when it ſtirs him up to new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, it exhibits not to him an inventory of his ſins as hitherto unknown, but either ſuppoſes them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43183:7"/>known in the law of nature, of which no man can be ignorant, or ſends him to learn them from the mouths of his Teachers; more than this, in the ordinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the holy Spirit in matters of inſtruction, I could never deſcry: ſo that to ſpeak of the Spirit helping in private, either in dijudicating or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting of Scripture, is to ſpeak they know not what.</p>
            <p>And truly till the World, eſpecially that part of it, whoſe underſtandings are of a more ordinary ſize, come to ſuch convictions as theſe, it is impoſſible but we ſhould be over-run with Doctrins of Devils; and it is very probable that ſome worſe Sect than that of the Quakers, if a worſe can come in their room, will e're long be at the door, in order to diſturb the minds of Credulous People, and to inſinuate ſuch Doctrins and Principles as tend to make them diſhoneſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral.</p>
            <p>And therefore if any fancies ſpring up in your heads, and you find your ſelves as it were ſmitten with it, and ready to adopt it into one of the moſt neceſſary truths to be believed and known, pray bring it to the touch-ſtone, to Scripture and right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and there conſider what weight it hath in it, and what plea it can make in a ſober and rational way, for its acceptance amongſt the great things of God. And if men did but take this courſe, the world would ſoon be reduced to order, and every man would keep his place, and live in thoſe limitted de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencies, upon the judgments of other men that are neceſſary for them, conſidering the difference of mens education and improvements.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another thing I lay down concerning this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit under the Goſpel, and the aſſiſtances that it affords men of pains and diligence, is this; that it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43183:8"/>works upon the intellectual part of man, and not upon the animal ſpirits of the body, the not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of which hath done a great deal of miſchief to the world; for the more ignorant part of mankind, finding ſometimes according to their fond affections they have for any perſon or thing, a great warmth upon their ſpirits, and a kind of eager fire burning in their bowels; all which ariſes from the preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their bodily ſpirits, increaſed by the ſtrength of their fancy and imagination: Why alas, let the thing be never ſo dangerous and deſtructive, yet away they run with it, as if the whole intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt lay at ſtake, and they care not what perils they expoſe themſelves to, what loſſes they ſuſtain, what hazards they encounter, nay nor what Authority they affront, ſo they may but ſee <hi>Sion</hi> happy, in the ſettlement of the preſent opinion they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo great a kindneſs for; and their ignorance and their zeal together hurls them out of all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and makes them deaf to all advice, and ſuſpicious of any man as an Enemy to the Kingdom of Chriſt, who attempts their reduction to more calm and temperate thoughts.</p>
            <p>But now certainly the Spirit of God, which comes with a deſign to refine the mind, and reform the manners of the Sons of Men, hath a better and more worthy ſubject to work upon than a company of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſpirits, hot and violent particles; which had they no ſuperiour powers to give Laws to their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would like <hi>Phaeton,</hi> ſet this world of Man on fire.</p>
            <p>No, no, the great deſign of this Spirit, is to mend that Soul which Chriſt died to purchaſe the life of: and certainly, when ever any man experiences its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine operations, he finds a vaſt alteration in the ſtate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43183:8"/>of his mind, his apprehenſions of things are far diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from their former ſelves, when he was under the command of luſt and prejudice; he then better ſees the nature of things, and thoſe ſeveral excellencies that are in them; he pitches upon objects which are every way more agreeable to the delights, as well as neceſſities of his ſoul, than the husks he formerly fed upon: And that love he has for God is not founded in the temperature of his body, in ſome preſent glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which ariſe from Rhetorical deſcriptions, but in a deep conſideration of the Divine Attributes and perfections of thoſe diſplays and communications that he bountifully makes of himſelf to the world; and his affections to the Lord Jeſus are not fixed upon him barely upon the ſcore of his Prieſthood, becauſe he fondly and fancifully expects to be ſaved by him; but he honours and loves him as his Lord and King, and teſtifies the truth of his love by ſubmitting to his Authority, and reſigning up himſelf to his will and pleaſure: and the Mans delight in God, is bottomed in thoſe rational ſatisfactions he hath had in a true performance of thoſe duties, through which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates himſelf to the intellectual and rational part of Man.</p>
            <p>Alas, thoſe touches upon the animal ſpirits, are but flaſhes, and vaniſh in a moment, upon which ſcore we read of ſeveral perſons in the late confuſions, who for a time made a great noiſe, and pretended to give as great a light to the world; in a moment after, the ſpirits flagged, and the courſe of their bodies alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſunk into the dregs of Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs, and drolled upon Religion as the product of a few melancholy vapours from the head, and not of a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional conſideration from the mind.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43183:9"/>
            <p>Whereas had theſe men been brought to Religion by the exerciſe of their minds and reaſon, about the Doctrins and Truths of the Chriſtian Religion, and by the help of Gods good Spirit, which never fails to raiſe and heighten the faculties, and to enlighten the object to ſuch laborious men, they had continued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to their profeſſion, notwithſtanding all diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements; for rational ſatisfaction, conviction of mind and judgment, cannot be laid aſide, but by great degeneracy and apoſtacy of mind, or elſe by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that out-weighs it in point of ſatisfaction to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And this was the way the <hi>Bereans</hi> took; for though there was the greateſt ſpirit in the World there, yet it is ſaid, <hi>they ſearched the Scriptures, whether thoſe things were ſo or no;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11.</note> that is, they made uſe of their Reaſon, to compare Propheſies with events, and thereby got the name of being more <hi>noble,</hi> and no doubt furniſhed themſelves with a more full ſatisfaction:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.2.</note> And St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (as his manner was) he went unto them, and three Sabbath days <hi>reaſoned with them out of the Scriptures;</hi> that is, he appealed to their judgments and underſtandings, and not to their, or his own private ſpirit: whereby he intimates, that that is the great method of conviction, and that the work of the Spirit of God, when ſuch things are offered to our reaſon, is to incline us to conſider and pauſe upon the evidence that is in thoſe arguments, and to ſix our thoughts in ſuch a manner, as not to ramble from what is propoſed, but to look into the ſtrength and force ſuch and ſuch Arguments are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended withal.</p>
            <p>I ſay this, this is the great work of the Spirit; and to judge of the truth of the Spirits morions, by the warmth of our affections, and not by the true light of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43183:9"/>our underſtanding, is to get into a Labyrinth, out of which we cannot extricate our ſelves, but by being guided by the clue of our Reaſon; and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing under ſuch deluſions as theſe, but a return to a mans ſelf, to an exerciſe of his intellectual powers, can ſave him, and prevent his being plunged over head and ears in ſin and Hereſie.</p>
            <p>And therefore let warm <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> cry down the uſe of Reaſon in Religion as long as they will, and call us carnal Preachers, for adviſing men to underſtand the reaſon of their Religion. Yet for all that, I dare deſire all thoſe who read theſe Papers, to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians upon no other account, than that they are convinced their Religion is the beſt in the World, both as to its grounds, and as to its deſign; and I dare aſſure them, that if they improve their minds by pains and diligence, they ſhall find con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſtrength infuſed into their ſouls by this good Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another thing I lay down concerning this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is this, that there is now nothing done by this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Spirit of God, which works upon the minds of diligent men, which contradicts and gain-ſays what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was ſaid or done by the extraordinary Spirit in the Prophets and Apoſtles; for the Holy Ghoſt is God, and ſo is Truth it ſelf, and cannot lie; and for any man to pretend he comes by vertue of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion received from him, and at the ſame time to ſpread abroad propoſitions of faith, or rules of life, which are not agreeable to what hath been already delivered down to the world, he ought to be rejected as a monſtrous Blaſphemer, a moſt vile Impoſttor, one that would thruſt the notion of a God out of the world, by rendering him contradictory to himſelf, changing his mind upon all emergencies, and making
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43183:10"/>that matter of duty to day, which not long agoe he declared againſt with the greateſt ſeverity. And though one would think ſuch a thing ſhould never be done by any perſon that wears a mans head, yet God knows thoſe looſe and ſcandalous times, in which our Fathers and we have lived, give us too ſad experience of it.</p>
            <p>What do you think of thoſe who pretend to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by nothing elſe but a light within them, and yet vent ſuch Doctrins of Devils as theſe are? to wit, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt is not God: That he died to be our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and not a Sacrifice: That they themſelves attain to ſuch a perfection of degrees as to live without ſin:</hi> And that which wants not its aggravation; namely, <hi>That the Magiſtrates have nothing to do to hinder them in ſpreading theſe looſe and deſperate Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though I could name other Parties of men, who come not much behind in ſome bad Principles; yet I am reſolved, ſeeing I am vindicating the true Notion of the Spirit that deſcended in the likeneſs of a Dove, to do it without any gall whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore intreat you, if at any time ſuch thoughts ariſe in your ſouls, as are flatly contrary to Scripture, or the like ſuggeſtions are made to you by others, to conſider thus much, that God cannot be deceived, neither can he deceive; and what he hath plainly given out as his will and pleaſure, that you may readily entertain, aſſent unto, and live in the practice of, without any danger whatſoever; and ſtill let holy Writ, with the help of the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of wiſe and good men be your Standard to prove Doctrins and Rules by, and then I am ſure you are ſafe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Spirit of God which now influences and act; the minds of men, is a Spirit of Wiſdom and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43183:10"/>underſtanding, as well as of warmth and zeal; and when any man is acted truly by this Spirit, though it may beget in him ſuch affections for things as may infuſe a convenient courage, and cloath him with a neceſſary boldneſs: yet for all that, he is kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his proper bounds, he runs not out to any exceſs, does nothing by vertue of a pretence to this Spirit, but what is very accountable to any perſon of true under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. And whoſoever he is that gives his paſſions leave to run before his judgment, that is acted by ſo prepoſterous a zeal, that he no ſooner is impreſſed, but preſently without conſulting his conſidering facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he makes himſelf ready for the undertaking: though the man may mean well, yet he muſt not, he ought not to bring in the Spirit of God to patronize his follies; for whereſoever it reſts, it (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) teaches no new things, though it helps us in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the old, and prompts to nothing but what is warranted to him by the evidence that is brought before his reaſon and underſtanding. And if it was not ſo, what ſtrange and horrid things might be done by a pretence to the Spirit of God, what Murthers, and what Rapins, what invaſion of other mens rights, and encroachments upon their liberties, and the like? And therefore 'tis very neceſſary, as well as expedient, for all Chriſtians, who would be a credit to their profeſſion, not to purſue any thing under a notion, they are ſpurred to it by the Spirit of God, unleſs they can give a ſober, rational, and wiſe account, both to themſelves and others, of the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the thing, of its conduciveneſs to ſome good purpoſes and deſigns; for ſtill the Spirit of the Lord that is ſent into the world on purpoſe to reform the minds of men, ſuggeſts no new things to them,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43183:11"/>but ſets on the old, which are already delivered from Holy Writ, and whether the Scriptures do not make us wiſe to ſalvation, whether we are not by them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to every thing that is lovely and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, I leave the moſt nice Critick to judge. Away then with thoſe men who are all fire, without any allay at all, whoſe heels are upon the go without any commiſſion from the Head; for theſe men are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the ſhame and reproach of Chriſtianity, and expoſe it to a thouſand reflections, from men who judge of it only by what they obſerve in others: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way (I ſay) with theſe, and give us the man who ſits down and retires into himſelf, and doth nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of the Spirit of God, but what he can give a reaſon for; this man indeed travels in a ſafe road, ſtands upon a bottom that ſhall never fail, and builds upon a rock which the winds and waves cannot daſh in pieces; for Reaſon is the ſame now that it was from all eternity, and we cannot fall into any danger, ſo long as we do the beſt we can to do things wiſely, and with our underſtandings; and I am ſure we ſhall not wrong the Divine Spirit, to give him his due ſhare in any action that is begun upon this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and finiſhed by the influence of ſuch conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, for he is called <hi>the Spirit of wiſdom and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, of counſel and might:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.2.</note> That is, he is not a Spirit that puts men upon headlong actions, that countenances any thing that is ridiculous and fooliſh, that is not well thought of and debated beforehand. This Spirit leaves men to the full exerciſe of all their faculties, and after a juſt ſatisfaction, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to purſue thoſe things we are ſo ſatisfied in, it gives us proportionable aſſiſtance; that is, it doth not do all for us, and we ſit ſtill; but when we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43183:11"/>do what we can, it lends us helps ſuitable to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and weakneſſes, and what is wanting in us, to do the work to Gods acceptation, this Spirit makes up: and ſo long as men are wiſe and prudent, and improve the powers of their ſouls by ſtudy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, ſo long they may expect the Spirit of God entring into their ſouls with all helps and aids agreeable to their neceſſities: And on the other hand, ſo long as men drive on fooliſh deſigns, and ſuffer themſelves to be acted by every plauſible Argument; why let their zeal be never ſo high and touring, never ſo hot and violent, yet I aſſure them their heat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the preſent temperature of the Body, and not from the concurrence of Gods Spirit; for ſtill I ſay it is a Spirit of wiſdom and underſtanding, and gives encouragement to no mans folly or indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though the Spirit of God be a Spirit of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, where it comes and is truly hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto, yet it does not exclude the uſe of means in order to obtain that Wiſdom: and though I would wiſh my tongue might ſooner cleave to the roof of my mouth, than I would do or ſay any thing to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement of this Spirit, yet have I no warrant to tell lies in its behalf, or to ſpeak more for it than it hath warranted me to do; and therefore I ſay this Spirit conſidered under the notion of the ordinary Spirit, for the extraordinary is ceaſed, does not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the uſe of means in order to obtain Wiſdom; for ſtill God having given us faculties of mind ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of inquiring and knowing, and having obliged us to the uſe thereof, and promiſed a bleſſing upon the uſe thereof, certainly he would not prevent our labour and induſtry by an extraordinary influence,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43183:12"/>when it might be done to all neceſſary purpoſes by the ordinary; no, no, we find this all along, that God never went out of the ordinary courſe of Nature, if it would do what he purpoſed without an extraro-ordinary interpoſal: and when ever he wrought Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, it was in order to ſuch convictions as dull Man could not receive without them.</p>
            <p>And therefore for any ſort of Men to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wiſer than all the world beſide, purely becauſe they are of a party, to whom they fancy the Spirit of God is alone married, is to argue themſelves the greateſt fools; for though it prompt men to nothing but what is Wiſe, yet it leaves men to the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves in Wiſdom, by exerting the powers of their own minds: and that man who does not take pains to increaſe his knowledge, who is not ſtudious &amp; thoughtful, I will warrant him ſhall be a Son of darkneſs, notwithſtanding that great light within, he ſo highly boaſts of; for it is not now as it was in the Apoſtles days, we have not things by Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by diligence and labour; the not right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding whereof, hath done a great deal of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to the world. For no ſooner have ſome perſons of little minds and ſlender thoughts, been brought over to a party of proud Men, who have monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized all Religion to themſelves, but preſently they have ſet up for Cenſurers General of the reſt of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as Reprobates and Caſt-aways, as men who have no ſhare in the eternal Decrees of Heaven, as Scum and Refuſe, and therefore fit for nothing but to give theſe conceited ones joy in the ruin and deſtruction of their Eſtates and Lives together; for if men did but believe the Spirit of God only aſſiſts them in every thing they know, and helps them to no rules of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43183:12"/>by private Inſpiration, but only encourages them in living up to thoſe they have learned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, there would be a great deal more modeſty in the world, and men would love more, and cenſure leſs.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Though the Spirit of God be a Spirit of Wiſdom, yet for all that, amongſt men that have this Spirit, ſome are wiſer than other; and the reaſon is plain, becauſe it does not by vertue of its operations, deſtroy mens natural parts, or thoſe acquirements they have made by different educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and you may find two men that have an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual aſſiſtance from Gods Spirit, that is, have their affections equally raiſed to things Divine; and yet one of them is of a far deeper underſtanding than the other, becauſe he hath had the advantage of an education before the other. And the Spirit of God, though wherever it comes, it makes all men good, ſtrengthens all good purpoſes and reſolutions, yet it leaves them to their own thoughts to find out Arguments for goodneſs, and to improve in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>And now for a concluſion. If any man ask me why I pitched upon ſuch a ſubject at this time, I anſwer, becauſe I thought nothing could more conduce to the peace of the Church, and to the preſerving the ſeveral ſubordinations of men, than the true and right ſtating of the Notion of the Spirit: For certainly did the People underſtand what has here been ſaid, Schiſm and Separation could not poſſibly have enlarged their borders as they have done; nor could Treaſons and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have found ſuch ſhelters and refuges as they have done. It was a falſe Notion of the Spirit
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43183:13"/>that brought in the Deſolations and Confuſions, the Murthers and Rapins of the late War; and by vertue of the ſame miſtakes, the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtand ready to run away from all thoſe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations that lie upon them, to be dutiful to the Laws of the Church, in which they live, and the ſubtle Deſigners, the cunning Crafts-men, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet did their buſineſs with the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by ſtrength of Argument and force of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but by gilded pretences of a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary commiſſion from the Spirit of God; and in purſuance thereof, by uſing uncouth phraſes, ſuch as are out of the common road of ſpeaking, and thereby inſinuating into the Peoples minds, an opinion that they forſooth are acted by a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Spirit than the reſt of the carnal World are acquainted withal. Whereas, let but theſe things be digeſted that I have named, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly that nothing is now done by this ordinary Spirit which contradicts what was done by the extraordinary, or that the Spirit now brings no new things to us, and we ſhall preſently return to ſober minds, and quiet and peaceable principles; then will God have his due, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> his: then inſtead of reviling Gods Miniſters, we ſhall give them honour ſuitable to the merits of their Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and with modeſty, ſo far as it is allowed by Proteſtant principles, ſubmit to their judgments without any pragmatical cenſuring of their more rational ſentiments: we ſhall then find, that we have no warrant from the Spirit to ſpeak evil of Dignities, to deſpiſe Authority, much leſs to rebel againſt them, becauſe they will not gratifie us in our more unreaſonable deſires; nor yet to leave the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43183:13"/>communion of a Church for ſome fancied corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. No, no, let us but be guided by theſe conſiderations, and I make no queſtion but we ſhall endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, and follow after thoſe things which make for peace, and whereby we may edifie one another. Which God of his mercy grant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
